Guide to the Robert L. Eichelberger Papers, 1728-1998 (bulk 1942-1949)
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Pictures Series, 1872-1984 (bulk 1942-1948).
  - People Subseries
    - Co-K
      - (Collins, Joseph Lawton, undated; Clark, Mark Wayne, undated; Cook, J. A., undated; Cooper, Gary, 1944 Jan., undated; Creel, George, undated; Draper, William H., 1947; Dunn, Floyd, undated; Edwards, Daniel Kramer, undated; Eisenhower, Dwight D., 1946 May; Elizabeth II, Queen of Great Britain, 1953; Emigh, Harry, undated; Gruenther, Alfred Maximilian, 1955; Halsey, William Frederick, 1949 Sept.; Hatfield, Lansing, undated; Herring, Edmund Francis, 1943; Hoover, Herbert, 1946, May; Howard, Roy, 1947 Feb.; Krueger, Walter, 1943 Nov., undated)
    - MacArthur, Douglas 1943-1948, undated, (2 folders)
    - M
      - (Maloney (of Chicago Tribune) 1947 Sept.; McCloy, John J., 1945 Oct.; McKinley, Jim, undated; Merkel, Una, undated)
    - N-R
      - (Northcott, John and Barbey, Daniel Edwards, undated; Pechkoff, M. Zenovi, undated; Robertson, Horace, 1947; Rogers, Gordon, undated; Roosevelt, Franklin Delano, 1934-1943)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor: Visit to Australia, 1943
    - S-W
      - (Sherman, Frederick C., 1946; Stimson, Henry L., 1940, undated; Van Oyen, Ludolf Henrik, 1943, undated; Wainwright, Jonathan Mayhew, 1945, undated)
  - Albums Subseries
    - Volume I, 1910-1918, Panama and Cuba, (1 volume, 1 folder) (Box 93)
    - Volume II, 1918, Sept.11-1921, Jan. 21, Siberia
    - Volume III, 1918-1921, Siberia
    - Volume IV, [see Oversize Materials]
    - Volume V, [see Oversize Materials]
    - Volume VI [see Oversize Materials]
    - Volume VII, 1945 Apr. 30-1946 Apr. 25, Occupation of Japan, Early Period
    - Volume VIII, 1945 Aug. 30-1948 June 29, Occupation of Japan
    - Volume VIII, 1945 Aug. 30-1948 June 29, Occupation of Japan, (2 folders) (Box 94)
    - Volume IX, 1945 Sept. 1-1946 Sept. 26, Occupation of Japan and Japanese Surrender, (2 folders)
    - Volume X, 1945 Aug. 30-Sept. 4, Japanese Surrender and Japan, (1 folder, 1 volume)
    - Volume XI, 1946 March-Aug. 30, Occupation of Japan
    - Volume XII, 1946 Sept. 4-Dec. 21 Occupation of Japan, (3 folders) (Box 95)
    - Volume XIII, 1946 Occupation of Japan
    - Volume XIV, [see Oversize Materials]
    - Volume XV, 1947 Jan. 10-June 27 Occupation of Japan, (4 folders)
    - Volume XV, 1947 Jan. 10-June 27 Occupation of Japan, (2 folders) (Box 96)
    - Volume XVI, 1947 April 7 Occupation of Japan
    - Volume XVII, 1947 May Occupation of Japan and Souvenir Pictures
    - Volume XVIII, 1947 July 4-Dec. 31 Occupation of Japan and Autographs of Dignitaries, (3 folders)
    - Volume XIX, 1948 Jan. 7-July 21 Occupation of Japan, (8 folders) (Box 97)
    - Volume XX, 1948 July 4 Appreciation Day Festival During Occupation of Japan
    - Volume XXI, 1948 Aug. 3-10 Occupation of Japan and Ceremonies at General Eichelberger's Retirement, (1 folder, 1 volume) (Box 98)
    - Volume XXII, [see Oversize Materials]
    - Volume XXIII, 1952 April 26-28 Visit of General and Mrs. Eichelberger to Australia
    - Volume XXIV, 1952 April 26- May 8 Visit of General and Mrs. Eichelberger to Australia
    - Volume XXV, undated The Artillery Center, Fort Sills, Oklahoma, (1 folder, 1 volume)
  - Miscellaneous Subseries
    - 1943-1959, undated, (6 folders) (Box 99)
- Printed Material Series, 1893-1962 (bulk 1946-1960).
  Contains books, including comic books, magazines and other material, chiefly relating to Eichelberger's military career. Arranged in chronological order. See also Writings and Speeches Series.
  - 1893-1952, (6 folders) (Box 100)
  - 1952-1962, undated, (4 folders) (Box 101)
- Clippings Series, 1918-1984 (bulk 1945-1955).
  Includes clippings chiefly relating to Eichelberger's military career. Arranged in chronological order.
  - 1918-1947, (11 folders) (Box 102)
  - 1948-1951, (7 folders) (Box 103)
  - 1952-1984, undated, (10 folders) (Box 104)
- Miscellaneous Series, 1911-1971, undated (bulk 1945-1960).
  Includes financial, audiovisual, biographical materials, and memorabilia. Documents Eichelberger's involvement in various organizations and contains information pertaining to his military career. Arranged into six subseries: Subject, Chronological, Guest Book, Audiovisual, Memorabilia, and Scrapbooks. Memorabilia and some audiovisual material are located in the Oversize Materials section.
  - Subject Subseries
    - Army Mutual Aid Association, 1949 Apr.-1950 Mar., undated (Box 105)
    - Biographical materials about General and Mrs. Eichelberger, 1942-1948, undated
    - Camouflage material, 1952
    - Deaths of Robert L. and Emma Eichelberger, 1961-1972
    - Documents pertaining to Helen Felder, 1943-1947
    - Financial papers, 1911-1959, undated, (3 folders)
    - Health Research Foundation, 1957-1960, undated, (2 folders) (Box 106)
    - List of Eichelberger's letters and papers, 1952-1961, undated
    - National Memorial Cemetery of the Pacific, 1949 Sept.
    - North Carolina Ports Authority, 1957-1960, undated, (2 folders)
    - War monument controversy (Urbana, Ohio), 1947 Apr., undated
  - Chronological Subseries
    - 1905-1962, undated, (6 folders) (Box 107)
  - Guest Book Subseries
    - 1946-1958 (Box 108)
  - Audiovisual Subseries
    - Films
      Arranged in order by size of film canister.
      - 1. (Box 109)
        - a. Silent color film of official residences of General Eichelberger in Tokyo, undated
        - b. Silent black and white film of General Eichelberger addressing a safety group, undated
      - 2. Japan
        - a. Gathering of generals and their ladies at the official residence of eneral Eichelberger in Tokyo, undated
        - b. Official residence, undated
        - c. Military review, undated
      - 3. Japan
        - a. Pearls, undated
        - b. Marriage ceremony, undated
        - c. Military review, undated
      - 4. Japan: Military review, undated
      - 5. Japan: Military review, undated
      - 6. Army football, 1948
      - 7. Japan: Eisenhower visits, 1946?
    - Phonograph Records
      See Oversize Materials
  - Memorabilia Subseries
  - Scrapbooks Subseries
    - Volume I, 1728-1940, (4 folders) (Box 110)
    - Volume II, 1936-1945, (2 folders)
    - Volume III, 1942-1947, (4 folders)
    - Volume IV, 1945, (2 folders) (Box 111)
    - Volume V, 1945-1949
    - Volume VI, 1945-1946, Japan, (2 folders)
    - Volume VII, 1945-1946, Newspaper Clippings and Mementos, (2 folders)
    - Volume VIII, 1948, (4 folders)
    - Volume IX, 1948-1954, (2 folders)
    - Volume X, 1949, (3 folders) (Box 112)
    - Volume Xa, 1949 Sept. 2, Dedication of the National Memorial Cemetery of the Pacific, (3 folders)
    - Volume XI [see Oversize Materials]
    - Volume XII, 1954, Fort Jackson, South Carolina, (2 folders)
    - Volume XIII [see Oversize Materials]
- Oversize Materials
  - Correspondence Series
    - Official Subseries
      - 1945-1949 (Box 126)
    - Personal and Official Subseries
      - 1952-1954 (Opaperfolder 4)
    - Condolences Subseries
      - 1961 (Opaperfolder 4)
  - Military Papers Series
    - Siberian Expedition Subseries
      - 1918-1920, undated (Box 126)
      - 1919 (Opaperfolder 2)
    - World War II Subseries
      - Campaigns: (Opaperfolder 5)
        - Leyte-Samar, P.I., 1944-1945 (Opaperfolder 5)
        - Luzon, P.I., 1944-1945 (Opaperfolder 5)
        - Mindanao, P.I., 1945 (Opaperfolder 5)
        - Palawan, Zamboanga and Jolo, P.I., 1945 (Opaperfolder 5)
        - Buna, New Guinea, 1942-1943 (Box 126)
        - Leyte-Samar, P.I., 1944-1945 (Box 126)
        - Luzon, P.I., 1944-1945, undated (Box 126)
      - Maps: (Box 126)
        - Mindanao, P.I., 1942-1945
        - Mindoro, P.I., 1944, undated
        - Nasugbu, P.I., 1944
        - Palawan, Zamboanga and Jolo, P.I., 1944-1947, undated
        - Panay, Negros and Cebu, P.I., 1945
    - World War II: Japan Subseries
      - Instruments and other materials of the Japanese surrender, 1945, undated (Box 126)
      - Maps: Japan, 1945, undated (Box 126)
    - Miscellaneous Subseries
      - Maps, 1940s (Opaperfolder 3)
      - Maps: Philippine Islands, 1938-1946, undated (Opaperfolder 1)
      - 1936-1948, undated (Opaperfolder 2)
  - Writings and Speeches Series
    - Chronological Subseries
      - 1944-1946, undated (Oversize-box 120)
      - 1945 (Box 126)
  - Pictures Series
    - Places and Events Subseries
      - Australia, 1952 (Oversize-box 115)
      - Japan: Occupation 1945, undated
      - New Guinea Campaign 1943, undated
      - Philippine Campaign, undated
  - Pictures Series
    - Places and Events Subseries
      - West Point, undated
    - People Subseries
      - Eichelberger 1948, undated
      - Eichelberger and Family: 1948, undated
      - Eichelberger: Formal Portraits 1941-1944, undated
      - Eichelberger: Miscellaneous, undated
      - Eichelberger: Commission of Robert L. Eichelberger as Major General, 1946 (Box 126)
      - Miscellaneous, 1938-1949, undated (Oversize-box 115)
    - Albums Subseries
      - Volume IV, 1939, 30th U.S. Infantry, San Francisco, Calif. (Opaperfolder OC:IV:1)
      - Volume V, 1941 Oct.-Nov. First Army Maneuvers (Oversize-box 118)
      - Volume VI, 1944 April 28-1945 March 30 New Guinea, Philippine Islands, Negros Islands, (2 folders) (Oversize-box 120)
      - Volume VII, 1945 April 30-1946 April 25 Occupation of Japan, Early Period
      - Volume VIII, 1945 Aug. 30-1948 June 29 Occupation of Japan (Oversize-box 118)
      - Volume XI, 1946 March-Aug. 30 Occupation of Japan (Oversize-box 121)
      - Volume XII, 1946 Sept. 4-Dec. 21 Occupation of Japan (Oversize-box 118)
      - One volume and one folder (Oversize-box 121)
      - Volume XIV, 1946 Nov. Visit to Japan of General Thomas T. Handy (Oversize-box 122)
      - Volume XV, 1947 Jan. 10-June 27 Occupation of Japan (Oversize-box 118)
      - Volume XVII, 1947 May Occupation of Japan and Souvenir Pictures
      - Volume XVIII, 1947 July 4-Dec. 31 Occupation of Japan and Autographs of Dignitaries
      - Volume XIX, 1948 Jan. 7-July 2 Occupation of Japan (Oversize-box 118)
      - Volume XXII, 1952 April 26-May 8 Souvenir of the Visit of General and Mrs. Eichelberger to Australia (Oversize-box 122)
    - Miscellaneous Subseries
      - 1920-1940s, undated (Box 126)
      - 1938 (Oversize-box 115)
      - 1940s, undated (Oversize-box 115)
      - Japanese drawings, undated (Oversize-box 115)
  - Printed Material Series
    - 1943-1960, undated (Oversize-box 116)
    - 1947, undated (Opaperfolder OC:III:8)
    - 1949, Saturday Evening Post, Our Bloody Jungle Road to Tokyo (Oversize-box 116)
  - Clippings Series
    - 1918-1948 (Box 126)
    - 1943-1948, undated (Oversize-box 120)
  - Miscellaneous Series
    - Subject Subseries
      - Land grant from James Monroe to George Handy, 1823, June 24 (Oversize-box 118)
      - Maps: 1942-1946, undated (Opaperfolder OC:II:3)
      - North Carolina State Ports Authority, 1959 (Opaperfolder OC:III:8)
    - Chronological Subseries
      - 1937-1957 (Oversize-box 120)
      - 1945-1947 (Box 126)
    - Audiovisual Subseries
      - Films
        - The Eighth Army Shield of the Free World (Box 2 (Ovsz. Film Box), Reel 41-A: Wire Container)
      - Phonograph Records
        - 1. Army Day Address, 1948 Apr. 6 (Oversize-box 113)
        - 2. BBC War reporting unit, undated
        - 3-8. Commemorative banquet given for Eichelberger, Asheville, N.C., undated
        - 9. GHQSWPA Recording of General Eichelberger, undated
        - 10. Memorial Day speech, Yokohama, Japan, 1947 May 23
        - 11. Memorial Day speech, 1948 May 31
        - 12. Merry Christmas 1945: Frazier Hunt, 1945 Dec. 20
        - 13. NBC radio broadcast of interview with Eichelberger upon his return to the U.S. for Christmas, 1945 Dec. 7
        - 14. Pyle-Eichelberger Interview, 1945 Aug. 31
        - 15. Radio 2UW Sydney: General Eichelberger interviewed by Lieutenant Colonel James Prentice in Sydney,Australia, 1952 May 2
        - 16. Recording of a portion of Frazier Hunt's broadcast about General Eichelberger, 1945?
        - 17. We the people, General Eichelberger / Jerome Edelberg, 1950 Aug. 18
        - 18. WFBC General Eichelberger 1949 Apr. 25 #1
        - 19. WFBC General Eichelberger 1949 Apr. 25 #2
        - 20. WFBC General Eichelberger 1949 Apr. 25 #3
        - 21. WFBC General Eichelberger 1949 Apr. 25 #4
        - 22. World Today, 1945 Dec. 24
        - 23. ARC Program- General Eichelberger, Colonel Stoval, Colonel Gray, Colonel Erkenbeck, Colonel Beans, Mr. Christensen (Announcer), Lieutenant Busbey, undated (Oversize-box 114)
        - 24. Armed Forces Radio Service Japan, undated
        - 25. a. Army Day Ceremonies-Speech by Eichelberger, undated
        - 25. b. Speech on deactivation of 77th Division, undated
        - 25. c. Army Day Speech for all troops in Japan (Armed Forces Radio Service), undated
        - 26. Description of Parade, Urbana, Ohio, and Eichelberger Address, 1947 Oct. 18, #1
        - 27. Description of Parade, Urbana, Ohio, and Eichelberger Address, 1947 Oct. 18, #2
        - 28. Description of Parade, Urbana, Ohio, and Eichelberger Address, 1947 Oct. 18, #3
        - 29. Eichelberger address: Opening baseball game Yokohama, Japan, 1946 May 4
        - 30. Eichelberger: Memorial Day Speech, WVTR, undated
        - 31. Hugh Sanders with General Eichelberger: Interview at Urbana Homecomeing, undated
    - Memorabilia Subseries
      - Cloth calendars (2), 1962 (Oversize-box 117)
      - Decorations (21), undated
      - Australian medal, undated
      - Merit plaque, n.d
      - Japan photo album (decorated mother of pearl, no contents), n.d
      - Japan Today: A Portfolio of Sketches, Tokyo-Yokohama Area, 1945-1946 (Oversize-box 119)
      - Engineers of the Eighth U.S. Army in Action: A Portfolio of Sketches Tokyo-Yokohama Area, 1945-1946
      - Japanese Prints, undated
      - Bust of General Eichelberger by Gozo Kawamura, 1946 Aug. 30
      - Oil portrait of General Eichelberger and General George Catlett Marshall, undated
      - Totem stick from New Guinea, undated (Opaperfolder OC:IV on top)
    - Scrapbooks Subseries
      - Volume I, 1728-1940, (1 volume, 2 folders) (Oversize-box 123 and 126)
      - Volume II, 1936-1945 (Oversize-box 118)
      - Volume III, 1942-1947, (2 folders) (Oversize-box 123 and 126)
      - Volume V, 1945-1949 (Oversize-box 119)
      - Volume VI, 1945-1946 (Oversize-box 124)
      - Volume VII, 1945-1946 Newspaper Clippings and Mementos (Oversize-box 124)
      - One volume and one folder (Oversize-box 123)
      - Volume IX, 1948-1954 (Oversize-box 125)
      - Volume XI, 1952
      - Volume XIII, 1961
- Accession #1999-0167, 1998
  This addition consists of 83 reels of negative microfilm made from the collection in 1998 as a part of the Japan and America, c1930-1955: The Pacific War and the Occupation of Japan microfilm series. A bound guide to this microfilm collection may be obtained from Research Services. Positive reels may be obtained from Perkins Library Microforms Department.
  - (Box 1)
    - Microfilm Negatives - Reels 1A-16
  - (Box 2)
    - Microfilm Negatives - Reels 17-33
  - (Box 3)
    - Microfilm Negatives - Reels 34-48
  - (Box 4)
    - Microfilm Negatives - Reels 49A-65
  - (Box 5)
    - Microfilm Negatives - Reels 66-83
Related Material
For the guide to the microfilm in accession # 1999-0167, see Japan and America, c1930-1955: The Pacific War and the Occupation of Japan in the Duke University Libraries online catalog.